Contact

832-262-8515 (Mobile) defreder2004@yahoo.com

www.linkedin.com/in/denisefredericksen-rn-bsn-ccrn-b874391 (LinkedIn)

Top Skills

Nursing
Critical Care
ICU

Certifications

Basic Life Support
Advanced Cardiac Life Support
Trauma Nursing Core Course
Certified Adult Critical Care
Registered Nurse

Denise Fredericksen RN, BSN, CCRN

Infection Control Practitioner at Kindred Healthcare Houston, Texas

Summary

- 14 years managerial experience, with 22 years supervisory and critical care experience.
- Current responsibilities include communicating, problem-solving, using critical thinking, with a strong knowledge for application of the Nurse Practice Act in the area of Critical Care and Intermediate Care Units.

BAY AREA REGIONAL MEDICAL CENTER, Webster, Texas 03/2014 to Present Director of Critical Care Services (CVICU, ICU, IMU)

KINDRED BAY AREA HOSPITAL, Pasadena, Texas 08/2011-03/2014

Director of Nursing

Director of Nursing for a 74 bed hospital, including 12 Intensive Care and 62 Acute Care Beds.

MEMORIAL HERMANN SOUTHEAST HOSPITAL, Houston, Texas

3/2008-08/2011

Clinical Manager II, Intensive Care Unit/Intermediate Care Unit Clinical Manager of a busy and progressive twenty-four bed ICU and eight bed IMCU at a 275 bed, non-profit, JCAHO Stroke and Chest Pain Center certified Level III Trauma hospital.

CYBERONICS, INC., Houston, Texas 3/2003-3/2008

Manager of Clinical Engineering II

Manager of Clinical Engineering under the Regulatory Department, responsible for the management and daily operations within the Clinical Technical Support Department.

MEMORIAL HERMANN SOUTHEAST HOSPITAL, Houston,

Texas

3/2002-3/2008

Supplemental Operations Administrator

MEMORIAL HERMANN SOUTHEAST HOSPITAL, Houston,

Texas

12/2000-3/2003

Clinical RN Education Specialist II

MEMORIAL HERMANN SOUTHEAST HOSPITAL, Houston,

Texas

8/1993-12/2000

Critical Care RN II

Critical Care RN in a progressive sixteen bed Intensive Care Unit at a 275 bed, non-profit, Level III Trauma hospital.

National Certification as an Adult Critical Care Registered Nurse (CCRN)

Advanced Cardiac Life Support (American Heart Association)

Pediatric Advanced Life Support (American Heart Association)

Basic Life Support (American Heart Assocation)

Fundamentals of Critical Care Support (FCCS)

Trauma Nursing Core Course (TNCC)

Experience

Kindred Healthcare

Infection Control Practitioner

November 2018 - Present (1 year 7 months)

Pasadena, Texas

Develops, implements, and continually monitors compliance of the infection control policies and procedures.

Maintains a surveillance system for detecting, monitoring hospital acquired and community infections, ensuring regulatory compliance.

Provides physicians and staff with updates of infection control.

Investigates outbreaks or clusters of infections. Monitors, analyzes, and interprets bacteriology reports and infection statistics, recommends appropriate control measures to prevent dissemination of resistant microorganisms and pathogens.

Consults with physicians, managers, and staff for the management of infectious and/or immune-suppressed patients.

Presents trended data to Hospital Committees.

Collaborates with local and state health departments in the prevention, control, and appropriate reporting of communicable diseases.

Participates in ongoing infection control educational programs for employees. Educates patients concerning infectious processes.

Acts as a resource person for staff concerning infection control.

Undertakes regular infection control audits and appropriate follow-up action where required.

Updates Leadership concerning any suspected hospital acquired infections.

Responsible for reporting hospital acquired infections to Centers for Disease

Control and Prevention.

Bay Area Regional Medical Center

Director of Cardiovascular and Critical Care Intensive Care Unit March 2014 - May 2018 (4 years 3 months)

Webster, Texas

Facility was closed on May 6, 2018.

Responsible for overseeing the build of a new 12 bed Intensive Care Unit/3 bed Intermediate Care Unit, a 12 bed Cardiovascular Care Unit and a Telemetry Monitoring Suite – new 104 bed facility successful opening date of July 21, 2014.

Designed, built, and maintain policies and procedures for areas of responsibilities.

Established inventories and maintain equipment and supplies for all areas of responsibility.

Team Lead on Cardiovascular Service Line to design and implement policies, procedures, and protocols.

Proficient in PA Catheters, CRRT, Art Lines, Chest Tubes, Vigilance II, Impella, IABP, and the care of immediate post-surgical CV patients.

Collaborated with other Directors and Chief Nursing Officer to obtain initial Joint Commission Accreditation upon opening and within the last two years obtained Bariatric Center Accreditation, Chest Pain Accreditation, ROSC Accreditation, Stroke Accreditation, and Trauma Level III Accreditation.

Effectively manages human and financial resources of assigned departments. This includes timely and constructive completion of performance evaluations,

disciplinary actions, budget activities and departmental goals.

Kindred Healthcare

Manager of Nursing

August 2011 - March 2014 (2 years 8 months)

Pasadena, Texas

Effectively manage clinical oversight for 62-medical/surgical/telemetry beds and 12 ICU beds. Supervise 125 nurses and employees, lead recruiting and hiring, manage employee review process and ensure compliance with state and federal regulations.

Oversee and manage clinical and support staff in patient care activities while maintaining a high level of staff morale.

Coordinates and directs staff to ensure patients' needs are met and hospital policy is followed.

Communicates appropriately and clearly to physicians, staff, and administrative team.

Consults and collaborates with other departments to ensure delivery of quality patient care.

Communicates the mission, ethics, and goals of the hospital.

Maintains a good working relationship both within the department and with other departments.

Process monthly reports for department performance and quality metrics.

Monitor unit budget to ensure financial objectives are met.

Contribute substantially to successful hospital JCAHO accreditation. Ensure HIPAA compliance. Policy management and oversight.

Achieved departmental goals and objectives by instituting new processes and standards for in-patient care.

Developed and maintained quality care systems and standards, including but not limited to, creating and improving medical protocols/guidelines.

Acts as Administrative representative in the absence of the Chief Clinical Officer.

Memorial Hermann Southeast Hospital

18 years

ICU/IMCU Clinical Manager II

March 2008 - July 2011 (3 years 5 months)

Clinical Manager of a busy and progressive 24 bed ICU and 8 bed IMCU at a 275 bed, non-profit, JCAHO Stroke and Chest Pain Center certified Level III Trauma hospital.

Directed day-to-day operations, including productivity, staffing, scheduling for approximately 95 plus full-time licensed employees, including six unit Clinical Coordinators.

Oversaw and managed productivity, quality compliance (Core Measures/Bundles), policy and procedure, unit protocols, and patient satisfaction initiatives.

Supplemental Operations Administrator March 2003 - March 2008 (5 years 1 month)

Weekend Operations Administrator of a progressive, 275 bed, non-profit, JCAHO Stroke and Chest Pain Center certified, Level III Trauma hospital. Responsibilities in this role included troubleshooting critical and non-critical issues involving patients, physicians, and staff, scheduling of stat and routine procedures, bed control to ensure patient placement to the appropriate level of care. Executive shift report provided at the end of each shift included a brief synopsis of the activities and issues addressed during that particular shift.

Clinical Nurse Educator II

March 2001 - March 2003 (2 years 1 month)

Responsible for meeting and planning programs to meet the educational needs for all staff (new and current) within the Intensive Care Unit, Cath Lab, and Post Operative Care Unit. Developed continuing education programs for nursing staff/physicians. Participated as an instructor in the Houston Area Critical Care Collaborative Group, teaching Cardiovascular Assessment to interns throughout the Texas Medical Center.

Critical Care RN II
August 1993 - March 2001 (7 years 8 months)

Critical Care RN in a progressive sixteen bed Intensive Care Unit at a 275 bed, non-profit, Level III Trauma hospital. Responsibilities included the total care of two to three patients including assessment, treatment, documentation, medication administration, patient education, discharge planning, assisting with procedures, hemodynamic monitoring, recovery of post-surgical patients, IV Therapy, evaluation of 12 lead EKG's, labs, ABG's, chest x-rays, and communicating patient's condition and results to studies to appropriate physicians. Additional responsibilities included functioning in the role of charge nurse, an ICU preceptor for new employees in the unit and delivery of a complete range of RN services and expertise, including Swan Ganz Catheters, IABP, and critical monitoring and treatments.

LivaNova Manager, Clinical Engineering March 2003 - February 2008 (5 years) Manager of Clinical Engineering under the Regulatory Department, responsible for the management and daily operations within the Clinical Technical Support Department that provided clinical and technical support to customers, surgery implantation support, logging of communications, device tracking and complaint determination in accordance with applicable regulations (21 CFR 803, 21 CFR 820.198 and the Active Implantable Medical Device Directives).

Effectively managed 20 biomedical engineers and nursing staff within the department.

Coordinated maintenance of company policy and procedures in regards to complaint handling, staff development, and device expert for staff and resource for internal and external customers. Participated on teams involved in new product development, corrective and preventive action, and investigations.

Education

The University of Texas at Arlington Bachelor's degree, Registered Nurse

San Jacinto College Associate's degree, Registered Nurse